# **BRIAN D. SWARTZ**

6038 Sharon Hills Road Portfolio: <a href="https://bdswartz.github.io/professional-portfolio/">https://bdswartz.github.io/professional-portfolio/</a>

Charlotte, NC 28210 GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/bdswartz">https://github.com/bdswartz</a>

Email: <u>briandswartz@outlook.com</u>

Mobile: (515) 868-6601

## **Summary:**

Full-Stack Web Developer currently enrolled in the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Full Stack Web Development Coding Bootcamp with previous experience as a Project Manager, Process Engineer, and Operations Manager. Skilled at troubleshooting, analyzing data, and improving processes and management systems in the petrochemical, nutraceutical, and metal industries

## **Core Competencies:**

Project Management

Data Analysis

Capital Management

Process Engineering

Operations Management

Compliance Auditing

Cause Analysis

Training and Talent Development

# **Technologies:**

JavaScript

❖ HTML and CSS

jQuery and jQuery UI

❖ Node.js

❖ Web DOM Document API

Third Party APIs: moment.js Geolocation API

Server-side APIs

CSS Framework: Bootstrap

Version Control: Git, GitHub

# **Employment:**

FMC Bessemer City, NC November 2014 – 2018

#### **Engineering Manager**

- **Project Manager** Managed a cross-functional project team that designed and executed a project to provide a \$1MM sealing system to the lithium hydroxide finished project dryer.
- **Facility Capital Portfolio Manager** Implemented systems to develop a 5-year capital plan based on the strategic goals of the business and allocate an \$8.5MM annual capital budget to support that plan
- **Divisional Technology Roadmap Team** Part of a team that was charged with developing the Lithium Division Technology Roadmap for the next 7-10 years. Worked with a team consisting of Process Technology, Research and Development, and Sales and Marketing representatives from the Worldwide Lithium Group to develop a technology roadmap that will was presented to the Lithium Senior Leadership Team.

## **Lincolnway Energy LLC**

Ames, IA

**April 2012 - May 2014** 

#### **Plant Engineer**

- **Project Manager** Coordinated cross-functional team (Engineering, Compliance, Operations, Construction, Accounting) to develop vision and strategy to convert the fuel mix in support of reducing greenhouse gas (GHG) emission for the facility.
  - Built the business case based on my analysis of true cost of ownership and shifts in US fuel markets including a detailed sensitivity analysis
  - Presented viable alternatives and recommendations to Board of Directors, Chief Executive Officer (CEO), Chief Financial Officer (CFO), and Plant Manager
  - Acted as Project Manager for the two main projects resulting from the analysis.
- **Process Engineer** Developed systems to collect operations data used in a quantitative model to evaluate and optimize fermentation performance.

- Collected operational data by pulling data from process database using database API
- Analyzed operational data using Excel Data Analysis tools (regression and multiple regression)
- As part of the operation performance measurement model, developed innovative ways to increase the reliability of results by creating new independent variables using existing data.
- Created new independent variables to recommend operational changes; increasing corn-toethanol yields by approximately 5%.
- Used process historian API to convert from time-based maintenance strategy to a predictive strategy

#### **Flint Hills Resources**

#### Menlo, IA

## **April 2007-March 2012**

- **Plant Manager** Facility leader accountable for all site operations in a 100 million gallon per year fuel ethanol production facility. Led a team of 6 direct and approximately 50 indirect reports.
- **Process Engineer -** Provided process engineering technical expertise for a 100 million gallon per year fuel ethanol facility.
  - Created engineering and operations training curriculum and training materials used to prepare a group of 35 newly-hired employees
  - Optimized unit operations including daily optimization of processes; decreasing raw material waste and energy usage.
  - o Created company-wide management system documentation for process safety compliance under OSHA 29 CFR 1910.119 (Process Safety Management).

### Cargill, Inc.

### Des Moines, IA

#### **June 1996-April 2007**

#### **Production Manager/Process Engineer**

- Managed a team of production and engineering professionals at a soybean oil solvent extraction facility. Notable roles include:
  - Process Pseudocoding Evaluated and improved process control pseudocode and computer interlocks using Distributed Computer System (DCS) documentation. Recommended Provox DCS control system programming changes to improve process uptime and efficiency.
  - Statistical Model Development Improved data quality of plant historian and developed statistical models in Microsoft Excel using plant historian API. Implemented new process control strategies and new product quality targets. Resulted in 8% decrease in energy usage. Model used as the basis for new business unit best practice to maximize product yield.
  - Equipment database creation Created tracking database using Microsoft Access. Created data input forms to aid maintenance personnel in populating the database with operations data.
  - o **Patent Valuation** Created a value for potential purchase of a patented process including sensitivity analysis of key cash flow drivers using Excel Data Tables.
  - Six Sigma Site Representative Designated as the location Six Sigma representative.
    Attended 40 hrs Green Belt Training. Participated with Business Unit Six Sigma Black Belt on finished product moisture control project.
  - Automation Documentation Created and documented process instrumentation standards for facility. Worked with a preferred supplier to develop a comprehensive document to aid purchasing engineers in procurement of instrumentation and process communication equipment that met current business unit best practices.

## **Education**

**Full-Stack Web Development Bootcamp**, University of North Carolina – Chapel Hill **Masters of Business and Administration**, University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA, **Bachelor of Science, Chemical Engineering**, Iowa State University, Ames, IA